all right
[Music]
few Studies have investigated the impact
of a plant-based diet on athletic
performance but the majority of the
studies that have been done show no
differences in endurance performance or
strength so while plant-based diets do
not seem to provide advantages or
disadvantages on exercise performance
what plant-based diets can do is reduce
the risk of chronic disease a point I
made in my video why all athletes should
eat plant-based diets because
surprisingly endurance athletes may have
more advanced atherosclerosis and more
heart muscle damage compared with
sedentary individuals so it's even more
important they eat healthy
but due to the favorable impact on
health it could be assumed that
performance would also be influenced by
plant-based diets uh let's take a closer
look at the available evidence this is
the most commonly cited review studies
connecting vegetarian diets to improved
Health are well established however the
evidence for this phenomenon to be
transferred to improve physical
performance in athletes is less clear
finding no difference at least acutely
shouldn't a vegetarian-based diet in an
omnivorous diet in muscular power
muscular strength short burst or
endurance performance the intervention
studies in this review however only
lasted days or weeks so being a
vegetarian for four days may not tip the
balance or even a few months but see
that's a considerable limitation these
are people who had been eating meats you
know their whole lives and subsequently
adopt a vegetarian diet only for the
duration of the study rather than
comparing participants who have adhered
to a vegetarian or meat containing diet
long term
this study compared Exercise capacity of
vegan vegetarian and meat eating
recreational Runners and found similar
maximum power output among all three
groups suggesting there's no significant
difference in maximum Exercise capacity
though that's at the same training
frequency time and distance perhaps
plant-based diets might enhance recovery
and allow such athletes to train longer
and harder a number of Studies have come
out since this review was published in
2016. what's the update well this study
compared the cardiorespiratory Fitness
and Peak torque strength differences
between vegetarian and omnivore
endurance athletes most of the
vegetarians were actually vegans at most
for at least two years and results from
the study indicate that vegetarian
endurance athletes cardio respiratory
Fitness was greater than that for their
omnivorous counterparts the greater VO2
max meaning a greater maximal oxygen
uptake a greater aerobic capacity as
measured on a progressive graded maximal
treadmill test to exhaustion though Peak
torque Peak strength based on leg
extensions didn't differ between Diet
groups bottom line these days suggest
that vegetarian diets do not compromise
performance outcomes and may facilitate
aerobic capacity in athletes
in this 2020 study all the plant-based
participants were eating vegan for an
average of four years so they were
essentially comparing those who ate me
for 21 years versus those who ate me for
25 years but after four years eating
plants you might expect to see some sort
of difference yet no significant
differences were noted for upper and
lower body muscle strength like in the
last new study both groups of athletes
were comparable for total body weight
lean body mass so age was significantly
higher in vegans compared with enforce
so that put them at a little
disadvantage yet still there it is again
significantly better aerobic capacity
then they had them peddled until
exhaustion and the vegan group lasted
about 25 percent longer 12 minutes as
opposed to nine minutes is that just
because their aerobic capacity is so
high no even after controlling for VO2
max levels there was still a significant
endurance advantage in the vegans the
researchers conclude that in the very
released a strictly plant-based diet
doesn't seem to be detrimental to
endurance and muscle strength and
endurance might actually be better in
vegans contrary to popular belief
[Music]